Imagine that when you walked in here this evening,
تخيل أنك عندما حضرت هنا هذا المساء،
you discovered that everybody in the room looked almost exactly the same:
اكتشفت أن الجميع في الغرفة يُشابهون بعضهم البعض لحد كبير:
ageless, raceless,
ونفس العمر والعرق،
generically good-looking.
وحسن المنظر بشكل عام.
That person sitting right next to you
الشخص الجالس إلى جانبك
might have the most idiosyncratic inner life,
ربما كانت حياته الخاصة الأكثر تميزاً،
but you don't have a clue
ولكنك لا تعلم
because we're all wearing the same blank expression all the time.
لأننا جميعاً نبرز ذات التعابير المبهمة طوال الوقت.
That is the kind of creepy transformation that is taking over cities,
هذا هو التحول المخيف الذي يهمين على مدننا،
only it applies to buildings, not people.
ولكنه يطبق فقط على المباني وليس البشر.
Cities are full of roughness and shadow,
المدن مليئة بالخشونة والظلال،
texture and color.
والملمس واللون.
You can still find architectural surfaces of great individuality and character
مازال بإمكانك أن تجد أسطح معمارية تعكس شخصية وتفرد كبيرين
in apartment buildings in Riga
في المباني السكنية في (ريغا)
and Yemen,
و (اليمن)،
social housing in Vienna,
السكن الاجتماعي في (فينا)،
Hopi villages in Arizona,
قرى (الهوبي) في (أريزونا)،
brownstones in New York,
الأحجار البنية في (نيويورك)،
wooden houses in San Francisco.
المنازل الخشبية في (سان فرانسيسكو)
These aren't palaces or cathedrals.
هذه ليست قصور أو كاتدرائيات.
These are just ordinary residences
هذه منازل عادية
expressing the ordinary splendor of cities.
معبرة عن الرونق المألوف للمدن.
And the reason they're like that is that the need for shelter
وسبب أنها بهذا الشكل هو أن الحاجة للمسكن
is so bound up with the human desire for beauty.
مرتبط للغاية بحاجة الإنسان للجمال.
Their rough surfaces give us a touchable city.
مَلمسها الخشن يمنحنا مدينة يمكن لمسها.
Right? Streets that you can read
شوارع يمكنك أن تقرأها
by running your fingers over brick and stone.
بتمرير أصابعك على القرميد والحجارة.
But that's getting harder to do,
لكن يصبح هذا الأمر صعبًا،
because cities are becoming smooth.
لأن المدن بدأت تصبح ملساء.
New downtowns sprout towers
الأبراج الجديدة في مراكز المدن
that are almost always made of concrete and steel
التي تكون غالبًا مصنوعة من المعدن والخرسانة
and covered in glass.
ومغطاة بالزجاج.
You can look at skylines all over the world --
يمكنك أن تنظر لناطحات حول العالم --
Houston,
(هيوستن)،
Guangzhou,
(جوانجو)،
Frankfurt --
(فرانكفورت) --
and you see the same army of high-gloss robots
وسترى الجيش نفسه من روبوتات من الزجاج العالي
marching over the horizon.
تمضي باتجاه الأفق.
Now, just think of everything we lose
لنفكر الآن بكل ما نخسره
when architects stop using the full range of available materials.
عندما يتوقف المهندسين المعماريين من استعمال جميع المواد المتاحة لهم.
When we reject granite and limestone and sandstone
عندما لا نستخدم الجرانيت والحجر الجيري والحجر الرملي
and wood and copper and terra-cotta and brick
والخشب والنحاس والطين والقرميد
and wattle and plaster,
والمعجون والجص،
we simplify architecture
فنحن نُبَسط الهندسة المعمارية
and we impoverish cities.
ونجعل المدن فقيرة.
It's as if you reduced all of the world's cuisines
كما لو أنك اختزلت جميع المأكولات في العالم
down to airline food.
لتصبح كطعام الطائرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Chicken or pasta?
الدجاج أو العجائن؟
But worse still,
ولكن الأسوأ من ذلك،
assemblies of glass towers like this one in Moscow
تجمعات الأبراج الزجاجية مثل هذه في (موسكو)
suggest a disdain for the civic and communal aspects of urban living.
تظهر ازدراء للمدنية والجوانب المجتمعية للحياة الحضرية.
Right? Buildings like these are intended to enrich their owners and tenants,
صممت هذه المباني لكي تثري الملاك والساكنين،
but not necessarily the lives of the rest of us,
ولكن ليس بالضرورة حياتنا نحن البقية،
those of us who navigate the spaces between the buildings.
نحن الذين نستخدم المساحات بين تلك المباني.
And we expect to do so for free.
ونحن نتوقع أن نقوم بهذا مجاناً.
Shiny towers are an invasive species
الأبراج اللامعة هي النوع المتعدي
and they are choking our cities and killing off public space.
وهي تتسبب في اختناق مدننا وقتل المساحات العامة.
We tend to think of a facade as being like makeup,
نحن نميل لتصور أن واجهة المباني هي بمثابة مساحيق التجميل،
a decorative layer applied at the end to a building that's effectively complete.
طبقة من الزينة تضاف إلى مبنى مكتمل لحد كبير.
But just because a facade is superficial
ولكن كون أن واجهة المباني هي شيء سطحي
doesn't mean it's not also deep.
لا يعني أنها لا تشكل عُمقاً.
Let me give you an example
دعوني أقدم لكم مثالاً
of how a city's surfaces affect the way we live in it.
كيف تؤثر أسطح المدن على طريقة عيشنا بها.
When I visited Salamanca in Spain,
حينما زرت (سالامانكا) في (إسبانيا)،
I gravitated to the Plaza Mayor
انجذبت إلى ساحة (مايور) العامة
at all hours of the day.
طوال اليوم.
Early in the morning, sunlight rakes the facades,
تتجمع أشعة الشمس على الواجهة في ساعات النهار الأولى،
sharpening shadows,
مبرزة النوافذ،
and at night, lamplight segments the buildings
ويقوم ضوء المصابيح في الليل بتجزئة المبنى
into hundreds of distinct areas,
إلى المئات من الأقسام المميزة،
balconies and windows and arcades,
الشرفات والنوافذ والأروقة،
each one a separate pocket of visual activity.
وكل منها عبارة عن جزء مستقل من النشاط البصري.
That detail and depth, that glamour
تلك الدقة والعمق، تلك الروعة
gives the plaza a theatrical quality.
تعطي للساحة خاصية مسرحية.
It becomes a stage where the generations can meet.
تصبح مسرحاً حيث يمكن أن تتلاقى الأجيال.
You have teenagers sprawling on the pavers,
تجد المراهقين مسترخين على الأرصفة،
seniors monopolizing the benches,
كبار السن يجلسون على المقاعد،
and real life starts to look like an opera set.
وتبدوا الحياة كأنها مسرحية أوبرا.
The curtain goes up on Salamanca.
ترتفع الستائر عن (سالامانكا).
So just because I'm talking about the exteriors of buildings,
ولأنني أتحدث فقط عن السطح الخارجي للمباني،
not form, not function, not structure,
وليس تكوينها أو وظيفتها أو هيكلها،
even so those surfaces give texture to our lives,
إلا أن تلك الأسطح تعطي نوع من البنية لحياتنا،
because buildings create the spaces around them,
لأن المباني تصنع المساحات المحيطة بها،
and those spaces can draw people in
وتلك المساحات يمكنها أن تجذب الناس إليها
or push them away.
أو تنفرهم منها.
And the difference often has to do with the quality of those exteriors.
والفرق يكمن غالبًا في جودة تلك الأسطح.
So one contemporary equivalent of the Plaza Mayor in Salamanca
ومثال معاصر مشابه لساحة (مايور) في (سالامانكا)
is the Place de la Défense in Paris,
وهو ساحة (دي لا ديفينز) في (باريس)،
a windswept, glass-walled open space
ساحة مفتوحة للهواء الطلق ذات جدران زجاجية
that office workers hurry through
ويمشي من خلالها الموظفون بسرعة
on the way from the metro to their cubicles
مغادرين قطار الأنفاق باتجاه مكاتبهم
but otherwise spend as little time in as possible.
وهم بذلك يمضون أقل وقت ممكن في هذا المكان.
In the early 1980s, the architect Philip Johnson
حاول المصمم (فيليب جونسون) في بداية ثمانينات القرن الماضي
tried to recreate a gracious European plaza in Pittsburgh.
أن يعيد إنشاء ساحة أوروبية جميلة في (بيتسبورغ).
This is PPG Place,
هذه ساحة (بي بي جي)،
a half acre of open space encircled by commercial buildings
نصف فدان من الفضاء المفتوح مُحاطة بمبان تجارية
made of mirrored glass.
مصنوعة من الزجاج العاكس.
And he ornamented those buildings with metal trim and bays
وقام بزخرفة تلك المباني بتقليمات وأخاديد معدنية
and Gothic turrets
وأبراج قوطية
which really pop on the skyline.
وهي بارزة بالفعل في الأفق.
But at ground level,
ولكن على المستوى الأرضي،
the plaza feels like a black glass cage.
تعطي الساحة شعور أنها سجن زجاجي أسود.
I mean, sure, in summertime
بالتأكيد، في وقت الصيف
kids are running back and forth through the fountain
يركض الأطفال حول نافورة المياه
and there's ice-skating in the winter,
و في الشتاء يتزلجون على الجليد،
but it lacks the informality of a leisurely hangout.
لكنها تفتقر إلى الطابع غير الرسمي واللقاءات المسلية.
It's just not the sort of place you really want to just hang out and chat.
وليست مكانًا يمكن أن تقصده لكي تلتقي أصدقائك وتتحدث معهم.
Public spaces thrive or fail for many different reasons.
أسطح المباني العامة تنجح وتفشل لأسباب عديدة.
Architecture is only one,
التصميم المعماري هي أحدها،
but it's an important one.
ولكنه السبب المهم.
Some recent plazas
بعض الساحات الحديثة
like Federation Square in Melbourne
مثل ساحة الاتحاد في (ملبورن)
or Superkilen in Copenhagen
أو (سوبركيلين) في (كوبنهاغن)
succeed because they combine old and new,
نجحت لأنها مزجت الماضي مع الحاضر،
rough and smooth,
الخشن و الناعم،
neutral and bright colors,
الألوان المحايدة والزاهية،
and because they don't rely excessively on glass.
ولأنها لا تعتمد على الزجاج بشكل مفرط.
Now, I'm not against glass.
في الواقع، أنا لست ضد الزجاج.
It's an ancient and versatile material.
هي مادة قديمة ومتعددة الاستخدامات.
It's easy to manufacture and transport
ومن السهل تصنيعها ونقلها
and install and replace
وتركيبها واستبدالها
and clean.
وتنظيفها.
It comes in everything from enormous, ultraclear sheets
يأتي بأشكال مختلفة مثل ألواح ضخمة بالغة الصفاء
to translucent bricks.
وحتى القرميد الشفاف.
New coatings make it change mood
وإضافة طبقة عليه تجعله يغير صفاته
in the shifting light.
تحت الأضواء المختلفة.
In expensive cities like New York, it has the magical power
هي تمتلك القدرة السحرية في المدن عالية التكلفة مثل (نيويورك)
of being able to multiply real estate values by allowing views,
حيث تضاعف من قيمة العقارات بزيادة الأماكن المطلة عليها،
which is really the only commodity that developers have to offer
وهي في الحقيقة السلعة الوحيدة التي يقدمها المطورون
to justify those surreal prices.
لتبرير تلك الأسعار الفلكية.
In the middle of the 19th century,
في منتصف القرن التاسع عشر،
with the construction of the Crystal Palace in London,
ومع بناء قصر الكريستال في (لندن)،
glass leapt to the top of the list of quintessentially modern substances.
قفز الزجاج إلى أعلى قائمة المواد الحديثة الجوهرية.
By the mid-20th century,
في منتصف القرن العشرين،
it had come to dominate the downtowns of some American cities,
أصبح الزجاج هو المهيمن على بعض مراكز المدن الأمريكية،
largely through some really spectacular office buildings
غالبًا من خلال مباني إدارية مذهلة بالفعل
like Lever House in midtown Manhattan, designed by Skidmore, Owings and Merrill.
مثل مبنى (ليفير هاوس) في وسط (منهاتن) من تصميم (سكيدمور، أوينجز وميريل).
Eventually, the technology advanced to the point
في نهاية المطاف، تقدمت التكنولوجيا لدرجة
where architects could design structures so transparent
أنها أتاحت للمهندسين المعماريين تصميم مباني شفافة لدرجة
they practically disappear.
أنها تصبح مختفية عمليًا.
And along the way,
وفي أثناء ذلك،
glass became the default material of the high-rise city,
أصبح الزجاج المادة المعتمدة للمدن التي يتزايد ارتفاعها،
and there's a very powerful reason for that.
وهناك سبب قوي بالفعل لهذا.
Because as the world's populations converge on cities,
لأن المزيد من الناس يتوافدون على المدن،
the least fortunate pack into jerry-built shantytowns.
وقليلوا الحظ فقط من يسكنون في مدن الصفيح رديئة الجودة.
But hundreds of millions of people need apartments and places to work
لكن مئات الملايين من الناس يحتاج إلى السكن وأماكن للعمل
in ever-larger buildings,
في مباني تتزايد مساحتها،
so it makes economic sense to put up towers
لذا من المنطقي اقتصاديا إنشاء أبراج
and wrap them in cheap and practical curtain walls.
وتغليفها بجدران وستائر رخيصة وعملية.
But glass has a limited ability
لكن الزجاج لديه قدرة محدودة
to be expressive.
أن تكون معبرة.
This is a section of wall framing a plaza
هذا جزء من جدار يحيط ساحة
in the pre-Hispanic city of Mitla, in southern Mexico.
في مدينة ما قبل الحقبة الإسبانية (ميتلا) في جنوب (المكسيك).
Those 2,000-year-old carvings
هذه النقوش التي عمرها 2000 سنة
make it clear that this was a place of high ritual significance.
توضح أن هذا مكان مهم لطقوس هامة.
Today we look at those and we can see a historical and textural continuity
بإمكاننا اليوم أن ننظر إليها ونرى استمرارية تاريخية ونسيجية
between those carvings, the mountains all around
بين تلك النقوش والجبال المحيطة بها
and that church which is built on top of the ruins
وتلك الكنيسة التي بنيت على الأنقاض
using stone plundered from the site.
مستخدمين حجارة أحضرت من الموقع.
In nearby Oaxaca, even ordinary plaster buildings
حتى مباني الجص العادية في (أواكساكا) القريبة
become canvasses for bright colors, political murals
أصبحت لوحات تتزين بالألوان الزاهية والجداريات السياسية
and sophisticated graphic arts.
وفنون تصويرية راقية.
It's an intricate, communicative language
إنها لغة معقدة للتواصل
that an epidemic of glass would simply wipe out.
سيؤدي انتشار الزجاج للقضاء عليها.
The good news is that architects and developers
الخبر السار هو أن المهندسين المعماريين والمطورين
have begun to rediscover the joys of texture
بدأوا إعادة اكتشاف متعة المواد المختلفة
without backing away from modernity.
دون التراجع عن الحداثة.
Some find innovative uses for old materials like brick
وجد البعض طرقاً مبتكرة لمواد قديمة مثل القرميد
and terra-cotta.
والصلصال.
Others invent new products like the molded panels that Snøhetta used
اخترع آخرون منتجات جديدة مثل اللوحات المصبوبة كالتي استخدمتها (سناهاتا)
to give the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art
لكي تعطي متحف (سان فرانسيسكو) للفن الحديث
that crinkly, sculptural quality.
صفة التجعد المنحوت.
The architect Stefano Boeri even created living facades.
أوجد المصمم (ستيفانو بويري) واجهات حية.
This is his Vertical Forest, a pair of apartment towers in Milan,
هذه الغابة العمودية وهي عبارة عن برجين سكنيين في (ميلان)،
whose most visible feature is greenery.
وأكثر ميزة ظاهرة لها هو الخضرة.
And Boeri is designing a version of this for Nanjing in China.
ويصمم (بويري) نسخة منها لمدينة (نانجين) في (الصين).
And imagine if green facades were as ubiquitous as glass ones
وتخيل لو أن الواجهات الخضراء انتشرت كالواجهات الزجاجية
how much cleaner the air in Chinese cities would become.
فكم سيصبح الهواء أنقى في المدن الصينية.
But the truth is that these are mostly one-offs,
لكن الواقع هو أن هذه مشاريع تنفذ لمرة واحدة
boutique projects,
مشاريع فريدة،
not easily reproduced at a global scale.
ليس من السهل إعادة تصنيعها على مستوى عالمي.
And that is the point.
وهذا هو المقصد.
When you use materials that have a local significance,
عندما تستخدم مواد لها أهمية محلية،
you prevent cities from all looking the same.
فأنت بذلك تتجنب أن تبدوا جميع المدن متماثلة.
Copper has a long history in New York --
للنحاس تاريخ طويل في (نيويورك) --
the Statue of Liberty,
تمثال الحرية،
the crown of the Woolworth Building --
تزين قمة مبنى (وول وورث)
but it fell out of fashion for a long time
لكنه أصبح خارج الاهتمام لوقت طويل
until SHoP Architects used it to cover the American Copper Building,
إلى أن قام مهندس معماري باستخدامه في واجهة مبنى (النحاس الأمريكي)،
a pair of twisting towers on the East River.
وهو عبارة عن برجان ملتويان على النهر الشرقي.
It's not even finished
وهو لم يتم الانتهاء منه
and you can see the way sunset lights up that metallic facade,
ويمكنك أن ترى كيف تضيء أشعة الشمس تلك الواجهة المعدنية،
which will weather to green as it ages.
التي ستتحول إلى اللون الأخضر بمرور الزمن.
Buildings can be like people.
يمكن للمباني أن تكون مثل البشر.
Their faces broadcast their experience.
تكون واجهاتهم انعكاس لخبراتهم.
And that's an important point,
وهذه نقطة هامة،
because when glass ages,
لأنه عندما يقدم الزجاج،
you just replace it,
تقوم باستبداله فقط،
and the building looks pretty much the same way it did before
وسيعود المبنى ليبدوا بذات المظهر السابق
until eventually it's demolished.
إلى أن يتم هدمه في النهاية.
Almost all other materials have the ability
جميع المواد تقريبًا لديها القدرة
to absorb infusions of history and memory,
على امتصاص معطيات التاريخ والذكريات،
and project it into the present.
ثم عكسها على الحاضر.
The firm Ennead
شركة (إينيد)
clad the Utah Natural History Museum in Salt Lake City in copper and zinc,
قامت يتغطية متحف (يوتا) للتاريخ الطبيعي في (سولت لايك سيتي) بالنحاس والزنك،
ores that have been mined in the area for 150 years
وهي خامات تم استخراجها من المنطقة طوال 150 عامًا
and that also camouflage the building against the ochre hills
كما أعطت المبنى منظراً منسجماً مع تلال (أوكر)
so that you have a natural history museum
لكي تحصل على متحف للتاريخ الطبيعي
that reflects the region's natural history.
يعكس التاريخ الطبيعي للمنطقة.
And when the Chinese Pritzker Prize winner Wang Shu
وعندما كان الصيني (وانج شو) الفائز بجائزة (بريتزكير)
was building a history museum in Ningbo,
يبني متحف تاريخي في (نينج بو)،
he didn't just create a wrapper for the past,
هو لم يبني فقط غلاف للماضي،
he built memory right into the walls
لكنه بنى ذاكرة موجودة داخل الجدران
by using brick and stones and shingles
مستخدمًا قرميد وحجارة ومخلفات كروية
salvaged from villages that had been demolished.
تم استخلاصها من قرى تم هدمها.
Now, architects can use glass
ويمكن للمهندسين المعمارين استخدام الزجاج
in equally lyrical and inventive ways.
بطريقة متناغمة ومبتكرة على حد سواء.
Here in New York, two buildings,
يوجد مبنيان في (نيويورك)،
one by Jean Nouvel and this one by Frank Gehry
الأول بتصميم (جان نوفال) وهذا بتصميم (فرانك غيري)
face off across West 19th Street,
يتواجهان في غرب الشارع التاسع عشر،
and the play of reflections that they toss back and forth
وهم يتلاعبون بالانعكاسات التي يتقاذفونها بينهم
is like a symphony in light.
تشبه سيمفونية من الضوء.
But when a city defaults to glass
لكن عندما يتم اعتماد الزجاج
as it grows,
وبينما هي تنمو،
it becomes a hall of mirrors,
فإنها تصبح قاعة من المرايا،
disquieting and cold.
مزعجة وباردة.
After all, cities are places of concentrated variety
فالمدن في النهاية هي أماكن من أنواع مركزة
where the world's cultures and languages and lifestyles
حيث يمكن لثقافات العالم واللغات وأساليب الحياة
come together and mingle.
أن تتجمع وتختلط معًا.
So rather than encase all that variety
ولذا بدلا من أن يتم اختزال كل هذا التنوع
and diversity in buildings of crushing sameness,
والاختلاف في المباني في صورة متماثلة خانقة،
we should have an architecture that honors the full range of the urban experience.
يجب أن يكون لدينا الهندسة المعمارية التي تحترم التجربة الحضرية بمفهومها الأشمل.
Thank you.
شكرا جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)